Guide to the D. H. Lawrence Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
D. H. Lawrence collection
1912-1963
GEN MSS 1093
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.34
(6 boxes) + 1 art object
The collection consists of correspondence, writings, agreements and contracts, photographs and artwork. The material documents Lawrence's writing career, his relationships with friends and publishers, and his travels in New Mexico, Mexico and Europe. Included is correspondence between his wife, Frieda Lawrence, and their mutual friends, and records relating to the rights to D. H. Lawrence's works after his death.
Lawrence, D. H. (David Herbert), 1885-1930
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired by gift and purchase, 1957-1989. For more information consult the appropriate curator.
D. H. Lawrence (1885-1930)
D. H. (David Herbert) Lawrence was an English writer and painter.
Scope and Contents
The D. H. Lawrence Collection consists of correspondence, writings, agreements and contracts, and photographs and drawings. The material documents Lawrence's writing career, his relationships with friends and publishers, and his travels in New Mexico, Mexico and Europe. Included is correspondence between his wife, Frieda Lawrence, and their mutual friends, and records relating to the rights to D. H. Lawrence's works after his death.
Arrangement
Organized into ten groupings: I. Pre-1960 Acquisitions. II. 1964 Acquisition. III. 17 January 1966 Acquisition. IV. 27 January 1966 Acquisition. V. September 1966 Acquisition. VI. August 1969 Acquisition. VII. December 1969 Acquisition. VIII. 1971 Acquistion. IX.1973 Acquisition. X. May 1989 Acquisition.
Authors, English -- 20th Century; English literature -- 20th Century; Europe -- Description and travel; Mexico -- Description and travel; New Mexico -- Description and travel; Drawings (visual works) -- England -- 20th Century; Photographs -- 20th Century; Authors -- England -- 20th Century; Lawrence, D. H. (David Herbert), 1885-1930; Lawrence, Frieda, 1879-1956
- Pre-1960 Acquisitions, 1912-1956; 1
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Gifts of H. Bacon Collamore, 1957-1958; Dudley Nichols,1959; and the Yale Library Associates, 1958.
  Arrangement
  Arranged by type of material.
  - Writings
    - "A Chapel Among the Mountains," autograph manuscript, 16 pages, [1912 August] (Box 1)
    - "Clouds," autograph manuscript, 12 leaves, written in an exercise book, signed on back cover, undated (Box 1)
    - "The Lovely Lady," typescript with corrections, 42 leaves, undated (Box 1)
    - "Making Love to Music," autograph manuscript, 14 pages; with note probably addressed to Nancy Pearn of Curtis-Brown added at end, 1929 April 26 (Box 1)
    - "The Novel: An Essay," typescript and autograph manuscript, 12 leaves, undated (Box 1)
    - Poems: "Ruination," autograph manuscript; "Last Hours," "On the March," "Rondeau of a Conscientious Objector," and "Tommies in the Train," typescripts with autograph corrections, 7 leaves, undated (Box 1)
    - "Sea and Sardinia," typescript with autograph corrections, 305 leaves; accompanied by an original map of Sardinia, drawn in ink, titled and initialed on verso by Lawrence, with an envelope addressed to Thomas Seltzer, undated (Box 1)
    - "We Need One Another," "Nobody Loves Me," and "The Real Thing," autograph essays, signed, 17 pages written in an exercise book labelled "Three Essays for Vanity Fair", undated (Box 1)
  - D. H. Lawrence correspondence
    - Falk, Bernard, 1929 February 24 (Box 1)
    - Mathews, Elkin, 1929 February 12 (Box 1)
    - Pinker, J. B., undated (Box 1)
    - Savage, Henry, 1913-1914 (Box 1)
    - Seltzer, Thomas, April 27 (Box 1)
      Scope and Contents
      Written on verso of a photograph of Lawrence.
    - Squire, Sir John, 1920 June 24 (Box 1)
    - Wilson, Charles, 1928 December 11 (Box 1)
    - Unidentified recipient, 1928 July 1 (Box 1)
  - Frieda Lawrence correspondence with Dudley Nichols and his wife Esta, [1936?]-1956; 2 (Box 1)
    Photograph of Frieda Lawrence and Robinson Jeffers enclosed with letter dated July 18, 1936. Some letters have postscripts by Angelo Ravagli, Frieda Lawrence's husband
  - Angelo Ravagli correspondence with Dudley and Esta Nichols, 1936-1956 (Box 1)
    Includes a letter dated August 23, 1956 describing the death of his wife Frieda.
  - Photograph of Lawrence by Nickolas Muray, undated (Box 1)
  - "The Finding of Moses" oil painting, undated (Box 7 (Art))
- 1964 Acquisition, 1915; 2
  Gift of H. Bacon Collamore, 1964.
  - Autograph letter signed from D. H. Lawrence to James B. Pinker; with typed transcript, 1915 May 31 (Box 2)
- January 17,1966 Acquisition, 1922-1949; 3
  Purchased from Willard Johnson on the William Robertson Coe Fund, George B. Alvord Fund, and the Walter McClintock Memorial Fund, 1966.
  Writings by D. H. Lawrence, Alice Long, and Mabel Dodge Luhan; correspondence between D. H. and Frieda Lawrence and Willard (Spud) Johnson and others; photographs of D. H. and Frieda Lawrence and friends; a drawing of D. H. Lawrence by Witter Bynner; and printed material regarding the death of D. H. Lawrence.
  - "Just Back from the Snake Dance," manuscript on verso of letter to D. H. and Frieda Lawrence, undated (Box 2)
  - "Mr. McKinley he aint' done no wrong," manuscript verse; with "The Cherry Tree," manuscript verse on verso, undated (Box 2)
  - "The Nightingale," manuscript essay, undated (Box 2)
  - Typescript about D. H. Lawrence by Mabel [Dodge Luhan], undated (Box 2)
  - Typescript carbon letter, signed, to "Chère Jeunesse" with cover note from Lawrence to Willard Johnson, 1922 October 12 (Box 2)
  - Letters, manuscript signed, to Willard (Spud) Johnson from D. H. Lawrence, 1922-1929, undated (Box 2)
  - Letters, manuscript, to Willard Johnson from Frieda Lawrence, 1938-1949, undated (Box 2)
  - Telegram from John H. McGinnis and George Bond to Spud Johnson, 1930 August 6 (Box 2)
  - Letters to Willard Johnson from the Centaur Book Shop and Curtis Brown Ltd., 1924-1930 (Box 2)
  - Note by unidentified sender to unidentified recipient, undated (Box 2)
  - "Drawing of Lorenzo" by Witter Bynner, pen-and-ink drawing, undated (Box 2)
  - Photographs of D. H. and Frieda Lawrence and friends, 1923, 1926, undated (Box 2)
  - "To D. H. Lawrence," manuscript poem by Alice Long, undated (Box 2)
  - Printed material about D. H. Lawrence, including issues of The Carmelite from March 1930, 1930, 1960 (Box 2)
- January 27, 1966 Acquisition, 1922; 4
  Gift of H. Bacon Collamore, 1966.
  - Autograph letter, signed by D. H. Lawrence to "Chère Jeunesse", 1922 October 12 (Box 2)
- September 1966 Acquisition, 1916-1917; 5
  - Three autograph letters signed from D. H. Lawrence to James B. Pinker, 1916-1917 (Box 2)
    Gift of H. Bacon Collamore.
- August 1969 Acquisition, undated; 6
  Gift of Ted Gikas, 1969.
  - Pen and ink sketch of D. H. Lawrence by Willard (Spud) Johnson, undated (Box 2)
- December 1969 Acquisition, 1914,1963; 7
  Gift of Professor and Mrs. Cleanth Brooks, 1969.
  - Autograph letter signed from D. H. Lawrence to Gordon H. Campbell, accompanied by typed carbon transcript and a typed letter signed from Sam A. Eisenstein to Cleanth Brooks about the letter with his typed carbon reply, 1914, 1963 (Box 2)
- 1971 Acquisition, [1913]; 8
  Gift of H. Bacon Collamore, 1971.
  - Two autograph letters signed from D. H. Lawrence to Henry Savage, [1913] (Box 2)
- 1973 Acquisition, 1914-1929, undated; 9
  Purchased on the Edwin J. Beinecke Fund, 1973.
  Volumes containing letters, postcards, writings, and photographs from D. H. and Frieda Lawrence to Catherine Carswell and her husband Donald Carswell.
  - Volume I of letters and postcards from D. H. Lawrence and Frieda Lawrence to Catherine Carswell, 1914-1919 (Box 3)
  - Volume II of letters and postcards from D. H. Lawrence and Frieda Lawrence to Catherine Carswell; with an autograph manuscript of a theme for a novel to be written by D. H. Lawrence and Catherine Carswell, and 5 photographs of paintings by D. H. Lawrence, 1920-1929 (Box 4)
  - Volume containing typed transcripts of letters and novel theme in Volumes I and II, undated (Box 5)
- May 1989 Acquisition, 1913-1933, undated; 10
  Correspondence, agreements, copyright registrations, photographs and other material relating to the publication of D. H. Lawrence's books in the United States. Represented in the papers are the firms of Thomas Seltzer, Inc.; Albert and Charles Boni, Inc.; Robert M. McBride and Company, Publishers; Mitchell Kennerley; and Little, Brown & Company, Inc. Correspondence of D. H. and Frieda Lawrence with these publishers is also included.
  Purchased from Book Block on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 1989.
  - Manuscript, typescript, and printed agreements, correspondence, and other documents relating to the publishing and copyright of Lawrence works, 1913-1933, undated; 7 (Box 6)
- Copies of collection catalog cards (Box 6)